

# Curriculum Vitae for Anis A. Ayati

### **Personal information**

Address: Spireaveien 12A E-mail: anis@xal.no

0580 Oslo Phone: +4799464312 26.01.1986 Nationality: Norwegian

### **Summary**

Born:

I hold a Ph.D. in Fluid Mechanics and a MSc. in Applied Mathematics from the University of Oslo. Before joining Expert Analytics, I worked as a postdoctoral researcher in the area of multiphase flows with focus on turbulence and interfacial waves. More recently, I worked as a senior data scientist in an industrial digitalization project, in which I developed a machine learning-driven monitoring and recommender system. My technical skill set includes python programming, statistical and spectral time-series analysis, machine learning and visualization.

I enjoy working in multidisciplinary teams and I thrive when given the chance to be creative in my work.

### Technical skills

Data analysis Spectral analysis, multivariate statistics, ensemble learning, deep lear-

ning, optimization.

Frameworks Numpy, Pandas, SciPy, Scikit-learn, Matplotlib, Keras.

Languages Python, Matlab, C++.

Tools Git, Azure Databricks, Google Cloud, Grafana, Latex.

### **Education**

2015	Ph.D. in Fluid Mechanics, Department of Mathematics, University of
	Oslo. Thesis title 'Dynamics of stratified gas-liquid pipe flow'
2008 - 2010	MSc. in Applied Mathematics and Mechanics, Department of Mathe-
	matics, University of Oslo.
2005 - 2008	BSc. in Physics, Department of Physics, University of Oslo.

# **Professional experience**

2019 -Consultant at Expert Analytics 2015 - 2018Postdoctoral Fellow, Department of Mathematics, University of Oslo. - 2018: Visiting researcher, Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, Princeton University, USA. - 2017: University Lecturer in Fluid Mechanics, Department of Mathematics, University of Oslo. - 2016: Visiting researcher, Department of Mechanical Engineering, PUC-Rio, Brazil. 2015 University Lecturer, Department of Physics, Norwegian University of Life Sciences. 2010 - 2014Ph.D. Research Fellow, Department of Mathematics, University of Oslo. - 25% assistant teacher in Vector Calculus. 2006 - 2010Student Mentor, TENK (now ENT3R), Faculty of Mathematics and

Natural Sciences, University of Oslo.

### Languages

Arabic Intermediate
English Fluent
French Fluent
Norwegian Fluent
Portuguese Intermediate

#### Personal skills

Communication As an agile data scientist, I learned to transform input from stakehol-

ders into technical solutions and to demo minimum viable products. As a researcher, I gained experience in publishing scientific findings in international relevant peer-reviewed journals and presenting my work in international conferences. As a teacher and mentor, I learned to break down complex concepts within mathematics and physics in order to explain those to students across the educational ladder, ranging

from high-school to university.

Management I have experience in defining, applying for and managing scientific

projects, as well as organizing and leading meetings and workshops.

### Some interests and hobbies

Academic Hydrodynamics, Aerodynamics, Optimization
Other Reading, traveling, football, martial arts, fitness.

# **Extended descriptions of selected projects**

Activity Smart Monitoring and Recommender System

Period 2019-2020

Role Senior Data Scientist

Staffing 2 Volume 100%

Description This project was part of AkerBP's digitalization program, Eureka. I

was involved in a production optimization team and worked on a use

case addressing produced water treatment.

I helped develop a digital assistant that provides root-cause diagnostics in the form of recommendation-based monitoring. I designed and implemented an analytics pipeline which combined physical modeling, data engineering and machine learning. I was actively involved in defining the solution as well as setting up and maintaining the application infrastructure comprising a data lake (Cognite Data Fusion), a python backend, cloud services platform and visualization dashboards.

Tools Python, Azure Databricks, Grafana, Cognite Data Fusion

Activity Detailed measurements of waves and turbulence in gas-liquid pipe flow

Period 2010-2018

Role Lead investigator

Staffing 3 Volume 100%

Description In my doctoral and postdoctoral work, I combined a variety experi-

mental methods in multiple experimental campaigns to quantify the dynamics of turbulence and shear-induced interfacial waves. The experiments resulted in large data sets consisting of high-spatial resolution images and various types of sensor signals. The data was subsequently structured and analysed using mathematical tools based on linear algebra, stochastic theory and spectral decomposition. Experimental insight was used to improve analytical models and optimize numerical

simulations.

Collaboration: During my Ph.D. I collaborated with a fellow Ph.D. student, whereas in my postdoctoral period, I supervised a Ph.D. student

and a MSc. student.

Tools Matlab, C++, ANSYS Fluent, Digiflow, LabView, LaTeX

Activity Development of an aerodynamic model for Vertical-Axis Wind Turbi-

nes

Period 2018 (April-October) Role Lead developer

Staffing 1 Volume 100% Description During my six-month research stay at Princeton University, I devel-

oped a numerical model that is able to accurately predict the aerodynamic performance of vertical-axis wind turbines. The model is an adaptation of the blade element momentum theory to the vertical-axis

configuration.

Tools Matlab, LaTeX

Activity Establishment of a research and education cooperation between Nor-

way and Brazil

Period 2015-2018

Role Project coordinator

 $\begin{array}{lll} \text{Staffing} & 10+ \\ \text{Volume} & 20\% \end{array}$ 

Description During my research visit at PUC-Rio, I helped establish a research

and education cooperation funded by the Norwegian Research Council and its Brazilian counterpart. During the project duration, 2017-2018, I organized and chaired several workshops, supervised and organized the exchange of Ph.D. and MSc. students and conducted collaborative research with my Brazilian colleagues. During Spring 2017, I acted as main author of a project application on behalf of the Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences, University of Oslo. The goal of the project was to tie together a large network of Norwegian and Brazilian universities and research institutions through the organization of an annual conference in Rio de Janeiro. I have acted as co-organizer and

session chair in the conference in the period 2016-2018.